<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="8"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[FOLLOWING JESUS
                                                The Essence of Discipleship

            Introduction

             “And He said to them all, if any man will come after Me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross
                                              daily and follow me.” (Lk. 9:23))

            God has set the Lord Jesus Christ as a standard and pattern of life and service for everyone to take cue
            from. So when He declared that if anyone will come after Him, he should deny himself and take up his
            cross daily and follow Him, He meant that every man desiring His glory must follow the path He trod
            and embrace His pattern of life and service without any option. This is the need for this study on
            following Jesus. It is a crucial part of the conditions we must fulfill in order to become disciples,
            learning of the Master. May you not be found wanting even at this point in Jesus’ name.

            1. “….AND FOLLOW ME.” Lk. 9:23.

            (a) Why must we follow Jesus?

            (i) We are lost. Rom. 3:10-18, 23, Isa.33:6, Eph. 2:11-12, Prov. 14:12, Gen. 3:8-9.
            Sin led us astray since the days of Adam. We were lost and have gone astray from the presence of
            God. Sin blinded us so much that we do not know the way back into God’s presence any longer.
            And for us to know our way back to God, we need help, a guide, and a visual aid. Jesus is the one; He
            is all we need.

            (ii). God has testified of Jesus and has commanded us to follow Him.
            Matt. 17:5, 1 Pet. 2:21, Heb. 1:1-4.
            God Himself spoke all the way from heaven bearing testimony about His Son Jesus Christ. He is the
            express image of His Person. The image of God lost in Adam is found in Christ and God has
            commanded us to follow in His steps if we must find our way back into His presence and regain the
            lost glory. He is the Pattern set for us by God to pattern our lives after. No other man must be our
            pattern. If we follow men, we must only follow them as long as they follow Jesus. God said, “This is My
            beloved Son in whom I am well pleased…” not “These are my beloved sons...”

            Though there were great men of God, great prophets in the scriptures, they are not the ‘pattern’ given
            us by God. We can only follow their lifestyle as long as it conforms to the life of Christ. Where their
            lives differ from that of Christ, we must look away from them and follow Jesus. God spoke in time past
            to the fathers by the prophets, but He has in these last days spoken to us by His Son whom He has
            appointed heir of all things. If you must please this same God, you must, in obedience to Him, learn to
            follow Jesus.

            (iii). John the Baptists’ testimony about Jesus. John 1:20, 29-37; Matt. 3:11-12; John 3:28-30.
            The reason why John was raised and why he came baptizing was to testify about Jesus and show Him
            to men so that they could follow Jesus. And he did. He did it to a point that two of his disciples left him
            and followed Jesus. Will you not also leave all others to follow Jesus? God testified about Him; John]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[also did. Out of the mouth of two or three witnesses, every truth is established (2 Cor. 13:1). May God
            help you to heed the call to follow Jesus.

            (iv) Jesus’ testimony about Himself and His mission.
            Jn. 14:6-7, Lk. 19:10, Matt. 11:28-30, Matt. 4:19.
            He is ‘the’ way, not ‘a’ way; He is ‘the’ truth, not ‘a’ truth’ He is the life. The way to God’s presence, the
            way into abundant living, into the holiness, power and the grace of God is Christ Himself. If you follow
            Him and His lifestyle, you will never miss it. He is the truth: His word and lifestyle is the truth about
            everything. When you believe and follow Him, you are sure to stand every storm of life. He is the life.
            Outside Christ, you will only enter into, and experience death everywhere.

            (v) Other’s testimony about Jesus. John 4:29, Matt. 27:54, Matt. 16:15-16.
            You can also be a witness unto Christ and your life can bear a powerful testimony about Him if you
            believe and follow Him as as some of us have done and are learning to do every day. Saying ‘no’ to self
            is not enough; coming under the power of the cross is not enough; you must ensure that you follow
            Jesus every step of the way.

            (b) Discuss what the phrase “follow me” generally means.

            (c) What does Jesus mean by saying “...and follow me?”
            Lk. 9:23 (KJV, AMP, LB); Jn. 13:15, Rom. 8:14, Jn. 15:14; Jn. 8:31

            Lk. 9:23.
                    NKJV. “Then He said to them all, ‘If anyone desires to come after Me, let him deny
                    himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow Me”.

                    Living Bible. “Then He said to all, anyone who wants to follow Me must put aside his
                    own desires and conveniences & carry his cross with him every day and keep close to
                    Me!”

                    AMPLIFIED. “And He said to all, if any person wills to come after Me, let him deny
                    himself - that is, disown himself, forget, lose sight of himself and his own interests,
                    refuse and give up himself - and take up his cross daily, and follow Me (that is, cleave
                    steadfastly to Me, conform wholly to My example, in living & if need be in dying also).”

            Following Jesus is not something to be assumed. It involves action. It means keep close to Me, cleave
            steadfastly to Me…’ that means, do nothing without me. Don’t separate yourself from me. Walk in the
            spirit. ‘You need a lot of diligence to ensure that you not only follow in His direction and walk in His
            steps, but you must also ensure that you not only follow in His direction and walk in His steps, but you
            must also ensure that there is no gap between you and Jesus. No gap of relationship, no hidden
            agenda, nothing between. It means living in accordance with the word of God. It means being led of
            the Holy Spirit always in all situations. ‘…Conform wholly to My example in living and if need be, in
            dying also.’

            That involves not only being ready to conform to Jesus’ example and pattern but you must actually
            conform and walk in His steps. You must be CONVERTED from your way of Life.]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[(d) Discuss what could make this step of following Jesus a hard thing both from Biblical examples
            and from your own experience. LK. 9:24-26, 57-62; Matt. 10:37-38, Mk. 10:21-23.
            How can we overcome these? Shame, desire to save one’s life (future security) because of fear of the
            future, possessions, children, father, mother, ambition, etc., are all things that could hinder, delay,
            distract or terminate a man from following Jesus. It all depends on who or what has gained control
            over your life. When you realize the high value of possessing Jesus and the Excellency of His
            knowledge, all other things and people will be to you as refuse, as it was unto Paul.

            What is that thing and who is that person in your own life that you know is capable of making it hard
            for you to follow Jesus? That thing (or person) must not overcome you. You must overcome it.

            (e) What are the necessary preconditions unto following Jesus meaningfully?
                  Lk. 9:23, Gal. 5:16-17.
               (i)  Leave your SELF behind, with your own interests together with whatever work you are doing,
                   which you cannot truly say it was Jesus that led you into. Matt. 4:19-22, Matt. 9:9, Mk. 10:28,
                   Lk. 9:57-62, Acts. 16:13, Acts. 9:1-6.

                   Surrender your life and everything of self to Jesus and wait on Him and for Him to instruct you
                   on what He will have you do. If He now tells you for example to go on doing the job you were
                   doing before for Him (and no longer for yourself), then do it (e.g. Luke the Physician in Col.
                   14:14; Erastus the City treasurer in Rom. 16:23). But if He tells you what He told Peter,
                   Matthew, Paul etc., be ready to follow Him. Allow Him to change your life, lifestyle, your career
                   and your all. Whatever He tells you to do, do it. Even if you have been faced with this earlier on,
                   you cannot afford to assume. And everyone who is not willing to take this step is not yet ready
                   to follow Jesus.

                   If you brush aside this requirement now, thinking you can bypass it and go on, that is a deceit.
                   Any day you seriously desire to be committed unto following Jesus, you will still meet this
                   hurdle. Rather than try to avoid it, it is better to surrender and make use of the grace (the
                   divine ability) of God to obey and fulfil this requirement.

               (ii)  Take up your cross daily. Gal. 5:16-17, Gal. 6:14, Rom. 6:11, Heb. 13:12-13.
                   Live victoriously over the flesh, the world and the devil daily as you walk in the consciousness of
                   what Christ did for us by the cross. Identify with Christ in every matter and over every issue,
                   bearing His reproach even if all were to forsake you. Be happy to stand alone. Take up your
                   cross daily. It is a necessary pre-condition that must be fulfilled in order for you to meaningfully,
                   faithfully and fruitfully follow the Lord.

            What is your experience in this? What are your difficulties?

            (f)  Discuss the dangers of trying to follow Jesus without fulfilling the above condition. Matt. 9:16-
            17, Rom. 8:6-8, Isa. 64:6, Heb. 9:27, 1 Cor. 3:11-15.
            It is not possible to please God on our own terms but on His. Whatever you do (for God) without
            fulfilling these conditions is like filthy rags before Him. You cannot please God that way. You will face]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[the danger of perishing or at best have all your works burn on the day of judgment. That is too costly
            and experiment to make with your life.
                 ‘He that overcomes…’ (Read Rev. 2:27, 11, 17, 26; Rev. 3:, 12, 21)

            There is a glorious reward for overcomers. If there were no battles to fight, the Lord would not have
            talked to us about overcomers. We must overcome the flesh, the world and the devil while here in the
            world by the enabling grace of God. The choice is yours. May God grant you understanding.

            (g)  Discuss God’s purpose in asking us to follow Jesus. Rom. 8:29, Heb. 2:10-11, Matt. 11:28-30,
            Matt. 4:19, Jn. 10:4, 5, 14, Jer. 29 :11.
            It is for our good, not for evil. It is for our good shepherding. It is not to make life difficult for us but to
            make us co-heirs indeed with Jesus. God’s purpose for instructing us to follow Jesus is to make us to
            be conformed to the image of the Lord Jesus Christ, something that cannot happen otherwise. Since
            there are no two-creation men in heaven only the New Creation Man, we cannot live the old creation
            life (the natural life) and hope to inherit the Kingdom of God with Jesus Christ. We can only be joint
            heirs with Christ not just by faith confession but by faith action. May the Lord enable you to pattern
            your life after Christ and to follow in His footsteps, not for one year or two, but throughout your
            lifetime in Jesus’ name.

            2. STEPS UNTO FOLLOWING JESUS.
            A. UNDERSTANDING HIS MIND (PROV. 23:7, PHIL. 2:5, PROV 4:23)
            This is the first step we must take in order to follow Jesus and walk in His steps. There is need for us to
            understand His mind, what is behind His action, what make Him to do what He did, how He looks at
            situations. Our steps in following Jesus will be arbitrary, meaningless and unnecessarily difficult unless
            we understand the thoughts behind His actions. This is necessary because as a man thinks in his heart,
            so is he.

            (I) Discus the mind Jesus had that make Him to take the steps He took.
            Phil. 2:5-11 (KJV, LB); Heb. 12:2-4, 1 Jn.3:16, Rom. 5:7-8, Heb. 2:17, Lk. 23:34; 1Cor. 1:27-29, Eph
            4:17-21, Phil. 2:5-8;
                  L.B. “ Your attitude should be the kind that was shown us by Jesus Christ, who though He
                  was God, did not demand and cling to His rights as God, but laid aside His mighty power
                  and glory, taking the disguise of a slave and becoming like men. He humbled Himself even
                  further, going so far as actually to die a criminal’s death on a cross”

            He never used His rights as God to defend SELF. Even to come down to the earth in human form He
            had to put aside His rights as God. He willingly laid Iit aside and did not cling to His rights as God even
            up to the time He was being crucified. You cannot continue to cling to your own rights and think you
            are following Jesus. You have rights…But at every point and in every situation you must be willing to
            release your right in order for the will of God to be done. Men may cheat you and deny you your
            rights. You will do well and be like Jesus by releasing and refusing to cling to your right.

            It was humility of heart that made Jesus to lay aside His glory and power and take upon Himself the
            form of a man. He bent down to serve men (even though He was God). And He went further in
            humility to allow ordinary human beings to crucify him though He was without sin. He could have
            shown them His power and punished them in revenge. But He did not. God would have counted that]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[as pride if He did, and He would not have fulfilled God’s purpose for Him to save us from our sins.
            Could you be manifesting your authority and power to revenge and defend yourself in the face of
            provocation and still think you are a follower of Jesus? How will God’s purpose for your life be fulfilled
            that way? That will render your salt tasteless and hinder you from being effective in serving God. It is
            necessary to understand and cultivate this mind, this attitude of meekness and humility and let it be
            rooted in us if we must follow Jesus effectively.

            You can also see an attitude of love, long-suffering, forgiveness, mercy, faithfulness, lowliness of mind
            exhibited by the Lord Jesus. Let this mind be in you, which was in Christ Jesus. Then following Jesus
            will be easy and His burden light. Look at His lowliness of mind in the following instances:

            (a) The way through which He came into the world. Lk. 1:26-27, Matt. 13:55, Lk. 2:5-8
            He did not come through the family of the king or the high priest but through an ordinary virgin
            espoused to a carpenter. His birth was announced not to politicians or high-class people but to
            shepherds. He identified with the lowly in His birth (Rom. 12:16).

            (b) His forerunner, John the Baptist, was rugged and simple. Lk. 3:7-9, Mk. 1:6-8
            He did not choose orators or men of high taste. He was lowly in His choice.

            (c) He chose ordinary fishermen (Barbarians) as His disciples, not Pharisees or Scribes.
            Are you lowly? Look at your friends, your choice of materials to us and people you work and walk
            with. Are you lowly?

            (II) Discuss His life goal in order to understand His mind. Ps. 40:6-8, Heb. 10:6-9, Jn. 4:32-34.

            He came with the attitude of obedience. His mind and His delight is to do the will of God, not to fulfill
            any selfish ambition. You cannot insist on satisfying your own pleasure and think you can follow Jesus.
            Let his mind be in you, which was in Christ Jesus, the mind to always do the will of God even when it
            hurts.

            (III) What understanding of His mind can you discover from His pattern of life, leadership and
            service? Matt. 20:25-28, Jn. 13:4-5, 12-17; Phil. 2:7, Isa. 53:1-9.

            His life pattern is that of humility and no reputation. He would not make a big name for Himself.
            Contrary to the world’s principles, for Jesus, leadership means service and the way into spiritual
            leadership is to bend down and serve. He had a mind of servant-hood. There is need to cultivate the
            same.

            (iv) Jesus never depended on Himself or wanted independence though at His disposal. Jn. 5:19, 30-
            32; Jn. 8:28-29, Heb. 5-8.

            He did not seek His own glory but God’s glory. He did nothing of Himself but whatever God wanted
            Him to do. He know that in man, there is nothing good. This mind must also be in you if you must
            follow Jesus meaningfully.]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[B. UNSETTING THE ‘SETTINGS’ OF THE OLD MIND.

            The way our old mind is set is the basis of our action and behavior. Hence the need to examine the old
            natural mind in the light of God’s word in order to unset it.

            (I) Discus the practical implications of a mind that is set. Rom. 8:5, Col. 3:1-3, 10-12, 15-16; Phil.
            3:15-16; 1 Pet. 4:1-2.

            Anything a man sets his mind upon is what he thinks about and what he aims at achieving. When you
            set your mind for example, on the belief that you cannot be influential unless you are rich , that is
            what will control your mind and that is what your mind will aim at achieving. It forms the bedrock of
            your understanding and behavior in order to achieve that purpose. If you set your mind on pleasing
            the Lord at all cost, that is what you will keep thinking about and always aim at achieving. Your desire
            will be towards the things of the Lord and your behavior will be to please Him. Just as the radio or
            television programs you receive depend on the frequency you set your radio or television to receive,
            you cannot set or tune your mind on the things of the earth and receive the things of the Spirit.

            Before you can set your mind on the things above, you have to undo the setting of your old mind. This
            is necessary before your mind can be renewed successfully with the word of God.

            (II) What is the mode of life and conduct that the old mind was set upon?
            Rom. 8:4-8, Eph. 4:17-20, Phil. 3:17-19, Jas. 4:4-5, 1 Jn. 2:15-17.

            It is clear that the old mind was set on what the human nature wants, not what God wants and no
            matter how you try to serve God with that mind, it will only achieve what the human nature wants. It
            was a futile mind that works all uncleanness with greediness. It was a mind set on earthly things.

            Look inside; what are the things you have set your mind to achieve in life or even in your marriage?
            Don’t rush over this. Bring them out sincerely; one by one, and see whether they are things on the
            earth or things above. That will help you to cry to God and unset those things as a preparation for
            setting your mind on things above.

            (III) For example, discuss the already set understanding of the world system (the old mind) about
            the following concepts:
            (a) Prosperity and success (b) Beauty

            Compare this with the biblical (or spiritual) understanding of the same concept. Gen. 39:3, 21: Josh.
            1:8; 1 Pet. 3:3-5 (GNB). What did you discover? In the world, prosperity or success is synonymous with
            wealth, Popularity, power, and position. But in God’s own perspective, none of those things makes a
            man prosperous.

            A prosperous man is someone who has God on his side. Joseph was a slave and later a prisoner; yet he
            was descried as a prosperous man because the Lord was with Him. What would make Joshua
            prosperous and have good success was not money or popularity; it was as he walked closely with God,
            studying and meditating on His word day and night.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[In the world, someone is said to be beautiful depending on her external appearance. But in God’s
            sight, even though may look beautiful in appearance, she is not beautiful in God’s sight unless she has
            a meek and quiet spirit. That is the set spiritual understanding of beauty.

            Before you can successfully have your mind set on things above, there is need to carefully unset the
            settings of the old mind and have your mind renewed and set on heavenly things. Your understanding
            of things must change and be in line with God’s own understanding of such things so that your desires
            can become right.

            C. CULTIVATING THE MIND OF CHRIST
            Cultivation requires clearing off, breaking up the ground and planting of a new seed followed by
            proper weeding and watering. Discuss how we can cultivate the mind of Christ taking the following
            steps:

            (I) Clear off the old mind. Jn. 3:3-7, Eph. 4:17-22, Ezek. 36:25-27, Ps. 51:10.

            There is need for a saving encounter with the Lord, a supernatural removal of the natural heart by God
            as you surrender to Christ to save you. It cannot be done by the energy of the flesh; the natural heart
            cannot be improved upon; it has to be removed and replaced. Thereafter the settings of your old mind
            have to be identified and put off deliberately.

            (II) What does that mean and how can we achieve it?

            Be concerned about the fallowness of your heart. Mourn over your situation. Let it touch your heart
            and not just your face. When you understand what you stand to lose if you continue with thorns and
            thistles in your heart, you will cry out. You will pray. A broken and a contrite heart God does not
            overlook. It is a necessary preparation for receiving seed, heavenly understanding on the soil of your
            heart.

            (III) Cleanse and renew your mind. Eph. 4:22-23, Rom. 12:1-2, Jas. 4:8, Eph. 5:26, Ps. 119:9-11.

            While the blood of Jesus washes and cleanses the heart from sin and its guilt, the word of God is God’s
            instrument for cleansing and renewing the mind. There is need for constant, daily, regular reading and
            studying of God’s word and hope to be renewed. The mind of Christ is embedded in the word of God.
            It only becomes yours as the word of God gets engrafted inside of you.

            (IV) Feed and fill your mind with the word of God. 1 Pet. 2:2, Col. 3:16, Josh. 1:8, Ps. 119:11, Isa.
            5:13-14.
            A sparing sowing of God’s word in your mind is not enough. Any little space or aspect of your life not
            filled with the word of God will soon grow weeds, the weeds of the natural mind. It will also become
            the loophole through which hell (the devil) creeps in to trouble you. Rather let the word of God dwell
            in you richly in all wisdom. Make no room (provision) for the flesh.]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[(V) What is the attitude and goal of a renewed mind? Phil. 1:20-21, Phil. 3:7-11, Heb. 10:5-7
            Set your heart, mind and body to know and to please the Lord at all cost. Let that be your goal, your
            only goal in life. Let it be your life pursuit. Then it will not be difficult to follow Jesus.

            CONCLUSION
            The Lord of Jesus Christ has perfectly won God’s approval over His life. Anyone who wants to walk
            with God and please Him must diligently cultivate His mind and follow the path Jesus trod. He must
            embrace Jesus’ pattern of life and service. The steps He took, the focus He had, and His manner of
            doing things must become the standard for anyone who desires to please God.

            Jesus Himself declared: ‘I am the way’; that means He is the method, the path, the strategy and
            pattern of living and service for mankind to follow.

            But no one can follow Him without having denied himself and taken up his cross daily. What is your
            response in all these?]]></page></pages></Search>